George W. Goddard Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
George W. Goddard Papers 1889-1984 (bulk 1940-1976)
MSS61803
Goddard, George W., 1889-1987
4,900 items
12 containers
5.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States Air Force brigadier general, author, and pioneer of modern aerial photographic reconnaissance. Correspondence, memoranda, writings, transcripts, research files, reports, patents, grants, diagrams, newspaper clippings, printed material, and photographs pertaining primarily to Goddard's career in the United States Army Air Corps and United States Air Force.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Interviews.; Foulois, Benjamin Delahauf, 1879-1967--Interviews.; Goddard, George W., 1889- Overview: A life-long adventure in aerial photography. 1969.; Goddard, George W., 1889-1987.; Roosevelt, Elliott, 1910-1990--Interviews.
Organizations
United States. Air Force--Officers.; United States. Army Air Forces--Officers.; United States. Army. Air Corps--Foreign service--Philippines.; United States. Army. Air Corps--Officers.
Subjects
Aerial photography--Research.; Aerial photography--Technological innovations.; Aerial reconnaissance, American.; Air bases--Ohio.; Cartography--Philippines--Luzon.; Military camps--Philippines.; Military reconnaissance.; Photographic reconnaissance systems.; Photography, Military--United States.; Stereoscopic cameras.
Places
Camp Nichols (Philippines); Luzon (Philippines)--Discovery and exploration.; Wright-Patterson Air Force Base (Ohio)
Occupations
Air Force officers.; Authors.
Provenance
The papers of George W. Goddard, United States Air Force brigadier general, author, and father of modern aerial photographic reconnaissance, were given to the Library of Congress by his daughter, Diane G. Bergh, in 1985.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs and slides have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the George W. Goddard Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of George W. Goddard are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1889, June 15 Born, Tunbridge Wells, England
1904 Moved to Syracuse, N.Y., to live with relatives
1910 Graduated, Washington Irving Preparatory School, New York, N.Y.
1912 1917 Free-lanced in Rochester, N.Y., as cartoonist and illustrator Staff artist for Coke and Iron Monthly, Chicago, Ill.
1917 Enlisted in the Aviation Section of the Signal Corps, United States Army
1918 Graduated, First Officer's School in Aerial Photography, School of Military Aeronautics, Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y. Appointed instructor of aerial photographic interpretation, School of Military Aeronautics Naturalized in Syracuse, N.Y.
1919 Assigned to McCook Field, Dayton, Ohio, by Gen. William "Billy" Mitchell; appointed officer-in-charge of aerial photographic research
1920 Promoted to first lieutenant and appointed officer-in-charge of aerial photography in the Office of the Chief of the Air Corps, Washington, D.C.
1924 Reappointed officer-in-charge of aerial photographic research, McCook Field, Dayton, Ohio
1927 1929 Appointed commanding officer of the Sixth Photographic Section, Camp Nichols, Philippine Islands
1929 Named director of the Army Photographic School, Chanute Field, Rantoul, Ill.
1934 Promoted to captain Supervised aerial mapping operations in central and northern Alaska
1936 Appointed chief of aerial photographic research and development, Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio
1940 Promoted to major
1942 Promoted to lieutenant colonel Developed the first stereoscopic strip camera
1943 Married Elizabeth Hayes
1944 Awarded Legion of Merit for work at Wright Field, Dayton, Ohio Assisted United States Navy with aerial photographic reconnaissance in England and France
1945 Appointed photographic disarmament officer and assigned to Germany Awarded Oak Leaf Cluster for the Legion of Merit and the French Croix de Guerre
1946 Assigned to Bikini Island in connection with atom bomb testing
1948 Promoted to colonel
1950 Received the Thurman H. Bane Award from the Institute of Aeronautical Sciences Granted patent for the flashlight cartridge and camera night aerial photographic system
1951 Received the Progress Medal Award from the Photographic Society of America
1952 Promoted to brigadier general and appointed director of reconnaissance, Allied Air Forces in Central Europe, Fontainbleu, France
1953 Retired from air force Photographic director, Bulova Research and Development Laboratories, N.Y.
1959 Assistant to the president, Itek Laboratories, Boston, Mass.
1962 Asked by Gen. Curtis LeMay to make stereo strips of Cuban missile sites with the stereoscopic strip camera
1969 With coauthor DeWitt S. Copp published autobiography Overview: A Life-long Adventure in Aerial Photography. Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday Retired from Itek Laboratories
1976 Inducted into the Aviation Hall of Fame and the International Aerospace Hall of Fame
1987, Sept. 20. Died, Boca Raton, Fla.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of George William Goddard (1889-1987) span the years 1889-1984, with the majority of the items dating from 1940 through 1976. The collection documents Goddard's military service, his writings, research, and public speaking activities, and his pioneering advances in the field of aerial photographic reconnaissance. The papers consist of the following series: Chronological File, Writings File, Inventions File, Oral History Transcripts File, and Miscellany.
The Goddard Papers reflect the drive and enthusiasm of a man whose aspiration in life was the technological advancement of airborne photographic reconnaissance. Goddard's lifelong ambition began in 1919 with an assignment to McCook Field as officer-in-charge of aerial photographic research. Although he had joined the army with the sole intent of flying airplanes, Goddard quickly developed an intense interest in aerial photography. He spent the next thirty-four years advancing its technology and demonstrating its reconnaissance abilities to a rather skeptical army.
As the unofficial spokesman for airborne photographic reconnaissance, Goddard wrote articles for popular magazines, gave numerous slide lectures to professional and military groups, and obtained press coverage to promote the use of aerial photography in reconnaissance operations. These efforts, coupled with his belief that "a full-time push by one man in a given direction greatly exceeds in efficiency part-time opposition by many men," led to increased funding for Goddard's research and development laboratory at Wright Field, improved technology and new inventions, and ultimately, the military's recognition of the remarkable effectiveness of aerial photographic reconnaissance. The technology now standard in reconnaissance today--night and long-range photography, color emulsion, and other methods that enable reconnaissance to be accomplished by high-speed aircraft at all operational altitudes--is due to Goddard's ingenuity and determination.
The Chronological File, originally arranged by Goddard for use in his autobiographical writings, documents his personal, professional, and military experiences as a pioneer in the field of aerial photographic reconnaissance. The series contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, and other materials pertaining to Goddard's military assignments in the United States, Philippines, and Europe, the operations of aerial photographic sections under his command, promotions and awards, and activities after retirement. The Cuban Missile Crisis, in which Goddard played an important role, is represented by only a few newspaper articles. Correspondence, notes, printed materials, newspaper clippings, and articles provide a wealth of biographical information on Goddard and disclose the high regard in which he was held by military officials and civilians involved in aerial photographic reconnaissance.
The Writings File contains articles, transcripts, correspondence, and working papers relating to Goddard's books, papers, lectures, speeches, and other writing projects. This file also contains book reviews, correspondence, and notes pertaining to his autobiography, Overview: A Life-long Adventure in Aerial Photography, and correspondence concerning Goddard's suspicions that the Itek Corporation, the United States Air Force, and Doubleday Publishing Company conspired to halt sales of the book due to its unflattering portrayal of Gen. Henry "Hap" Arnold. Another notable item is an article published by National Geographic Magazine in 1930 entitled, "The Unexplored Philippines from the Air." Illustrated with photographs taken by Goddard, the article describes his experiences in 1928 as commanding officer of the Sixth Photographic Section, charged with making a photographic mosaic map of the unexplored northeast corner of Luzon Island.
The Inventions File consists primarily of patent grants, reports, and diagrams relating to Goddard's patented inventions. Also included in this series are correspondence, notes, and printed materials pertaining to the stereoscopic strip camera. This camera, which was never patented, was developed by Goddard and his colleagues in 1942 at Wright Field and was used to make stereo strips of Cuban missile sites in 1962.
The Oral History Transcripts File contains transcripts of oral history interviews conducted by Goddard for use in his autobiographical writings. The interviewees were military officers and civilians interested or active in the science of aerial photographic reconnaissance during the years of Goddard's military service, including Benjamin Foulois, Elliott Roosevelt, and Dwight D. Eisenhower. Also included are several interviews with Goddard conducted by others. Original tapes of most of the interviews have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division of the Library.
The final series in the collection, Miscellany, consists primarily of printed materials collected by Goddard. The file contains books, journals, and informational reports, mostly regarding the use of aerial photographic reconnaissance in World War II. Photographs of Goddard and of his family and friends, several stereograph cards, and a 3-D photograph with stereoscopic glasses are also included.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Chronological File, 1889-1983
Writings File, 1925-1981
Inventions File, 1933-1967
Oral History Transcripts File, 1963-1969
Miscellany, 1910-1984
Container List
- Chronological File, 1889-1983 (Box 1-5)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, notes, newspaper clippings, articles, certificates, photographs, and printed matter relating to the personal, military, and business activities of Goddard.
  Arrangement is by calendar year. Materials within each year are arranged in the following order: correspondence, military papers, certificates and awards, newspaper clippings, printed matter, photographs, and notes.
  - 1889-1940, (13 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1941-1950, (10 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1951-1971, (9 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1972-1977, (7 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1978-1983, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5)
- Writings File, 1925-1981 (Box 6-8)
  Draft copies, articles, transcripts, correspondence, notes, working papers, and research materials relating to Goddard's writing projects.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by type of material and chronological thereunder.
  - Articles, 1930-1951, undated (Box 6)
  - Book projects (Box 6)
    - "For the Record," undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - "George Goddard's Sketch Book," 1975 (Box 6)
    - "Goddard's Archives," 1977-1980 (Box 6)
    - Overview: A Life-long Adventure in Aerial Photography (Box 6)
      - Book reviews, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1966-1981, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Movie idea, 1971, undated (Box 7)
    - "Pioneering Years in Aerial Photography" (unpublished, distributed by Goddard to educational institutions), 1969-1973 (Box 7)
  - Remarks (Box 7)
    - General, 1942-1975, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Notes and slide captions, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Research materials, 1925-1975, undated, (1 folder); (3 folders) (Box 7, Box 8)
- Inventions File, 1933-1967 (Box 8)
  Patent grants, reports, diagrams, correspondence, notes, and printed matter.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by title of invention.
  - Aerial camera, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Aerial and ground photographic equipment for photographing nuclear bomb explosions, 1961 (Box 8)
  - Automatic aerial photography, 1959 (Box 8)
  - Automatic photographic apparatus, 1933 (Box 8)
  - Flashlight cartridge and camera night aerial photographic system, 1945-1950, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Method of illuminating areas viewed from an aircraft at night, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Multiple-sensor airborne reconnaissance systems, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Strip camera, 1945-1949, 1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
- Oral History Transcripts File, 1963-1969 (Box 9-10)
  Transcripts of oral history interviews.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by surname of interviewee. One folder containing lists and descriptions of the interviewees precedes the transcripts. Although some transcripts are not dated, all of the interviews took place between 1963 and 1969.
  - List of names (Box 9)
  - Abrams-Baker (Box 9)
  - Baudu-Cahill (Box 9)
  - Carroll-Curry (Box 9)
  - Davidson-Eisenhower (Box 9)
  - Fairchild-Gilbert (Box 9)
  - Goddard-Hancock (Box 10)
  - Hardy-Hoskinson (Box 10)
  - Kauffman-Knerr (Box 10)
  - Leghorn-O'Brien (Box 10)
  - Odenthal-Pierstorff (Box 10)
  - Reinhartz (Box 10)
  - Richards-Steakley (Box 10)
  - Steichen-Tarkington (Box 10)
  - Troidle-Winston (Box 10)
- Miscellany, 1910-1984 (Box 11-12)
  Books, journals, manuals, pamphlets, photographs, press kits, reports, studies, stereograph cards, a 3-D photograph with stereoscopic glasses, and other materials.
  Arrangement is alphabetical by type of material.
  - Books, 1957, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Journals and magazines, 1936-1956, 1976, undated, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Manuals, 1955 (Box 11)
  - Pamphlets, 1955 (Box 12)
  - Photographs, 1910-1984, undated (Box 12)
  - Press kits, 1975 (Box 12)
  - Reports, 1935-1945, 1963-1975, (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Stereograph and 3-D cards, miscellaneous, undated (Box 12)
  - Studies, 1961, undated, (2 folders) (Box 12)